<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ideas | Bohumír Zámečník]]></title>
  <link href="http://bohumirzamecnik.cz/blog/categories/ideas/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bohumirzamecnik.cz/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-29T00:32:06+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://bohumirzamecnik.cz/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bohumír Zámečník]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's Share the Ideas With the World!]]></title>
    <link href="http://bohumirzamecnik.cz/blog/2014/lets-share-the-ideas-with-the-world/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://bohumirzamecnik.cz/blog/2014/lets-share-the-ideas-with-the-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What&rsquo;s better? A stream of brilliant ideas rotting in a shelf or one great idea living its own life beyond the author imagination and helping many other people? Have you ever considered what will remain after you pass away? I&rsquo;ve thought a bit about those questions and guess what I realized.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>You&rsquo;d probably agree a week lacking enough sleep is certainly not a fertile soil for being inspired with great ideas. Last Wednesday I finally tried to fall asleep after a long tiring day but I couldn&rsquo;t. A stream of interesting ideas and questions started coming to my mind. Or reminding me that I should not forget about them as this happens to me quite often. To give you some impression:</p>

<ul>
<li>Machine Learning on chemometrical data.</li>
<li>Sonification of time-series.</li>
<li>Aggregated statistics on time-series.</li>
<li>Stochastic sampling of the time-frequency plane.</li>
<li>Visualizing a chord time-series as a curved 3D tube.</li>
<li>Measuring and visualizing the tuning profile of a piano.</li>
<li>Measuring and visualizing information flow in songs.</li>
<li>Visualizing chord progressions with both 1-step and 7-step connections using Hamiltonian circles.</li>
<li>Song visualization via non-linear dimensionality reduction to 2D or even 1D time-series.</li>
<li>A fast implementation of SliCQ and frequency reassignment with good API.</li>
<li>Blog about refactoring open-source projects.</li>
<li>Small programming projects in many fields &ndash; code &amp; e-books.</li>
<li>Clustering with autoencoder.</li>
<li>Using bilateral filter or content-aware fill on sound instead of images.</li>
<li>Deep learning for sound compression.</li>
<li>What would I start coding if I was 6 years old again but with today&rsquo;s knowledge.</li>
<li>Did people developed such farther than other animals due to fire and music?</li>
</ul>


<p>I was writing them down and finally an important question appeared.</p>

<blockquote><p>What if I shared all my ideas with the world?</p></blockquote>

<p>My problem is not having enough interesting ideas &ndash; although I&rsquo;m certainly far from the smartest people around, I&rsquo;ve been gifted with a decent fantasy and I&rsquo;ve been training it whole my life. The problem to utilize the holy raw material and bring the ideas to life so they actually help people. Without it they&rsquo;re useless and empty. Throughout the years I had ideas for many dissertations and I don&rsquo;t have so much time and abilities to finished them all alone. Actually I delved into practice instead of doing a PhD, just to be able to fiddle with my projects.</p>

<p>Recently I wondered what to do with the ever growing list of project and research ideas that I gathered in many years. I always had a mindset that each one idea could be turned into product and sharing the idea would prevent me from making money from it someday since someone could be faster &ndash; and have a free lunch. So the majority of my ideas are still in rotting a shelf. Worse than not having them at all, each time I look at them they always remind me that I&rsquo;m wasting them tremendously.</p>

<p>Earlier this year I tried to turn several ideas into product (eg. the <a href="http://harmoneye.com/">HarmonEye</a> application for music visualization, etc.). Unfortunately I focused too much on the technical aspects and less on the actual people and problems. Although <a href="http://buildandlaunch.net/courses/">I learned that I should build audience first</a>, I didn&rsquo;t do it properly and rather coded furiously.</p>

<p>Finally it made me completely tired without having the product running. So I made a <a href="http://bohumirzamecnik.cz/blog/categories/scandinavia-2014/">month-long road trip Scandinavia</a>, cleaned my head, decided to focus on Machine Learning and took another job. And most importantly I&rsquo;m finally trying hard to learn and train an effective process of realizing the projects, GTD. I realized that for a knowledge worker this is the one of most important generally usable tools ever. Yearst ago I knew I should probably master it but I was always feeling to busy or lazy to actually start.</p>

<p>Recently I was thinking ahead of time of one moment in life that will certainly come, although noone knows when:</p>

<blockquote><p>What work would I leave behind me to the society when I pass some day?</p>

<p>How did I help other people solve their problems?</p></blockquote>

<p>This is, in my opinion, a very good tool to distinguish what is important and what isn&rsquo;t.</p>

<p>So I realized ideas that appear in my brain are worthless if I just put them to some &ldquo;icebox&rdquo; and never share or implement them in order help other people. Having new ideas connecting multiple fields is not so expensive for me today. I cannot control them. They just instantly appear and then chase me until I write them down.</p>

<p>Partly it is a gift, but mainly it is due to the continous training and enormous stimuli from the society, in the last few decades enormously accelerated by the Internet. We live in a strange, yet wonderful era. I realize the conditions won&rsquo;t be there forever, so in fact I feel a kind of responsibility.</p>

<p>So what are the pros and cons of sharing the ideas with the world?</p>

<ul>
<li>(+) While I write a raw idea down for others I have to clarify its goals and produce a presentable unit of information. Note that this naturally corresponds is the first step in GTD or Agile.</li>
<li>(+) When I have clarified the goals there&rsquo;s a much higher chance I&rsquo;ll actually make the idea.</li>
<li>(+) If I publish a idea, eg. on my blog, someone gets interested and actually builds a product, I might still benefit from the solution, even though I didn&rsquo;t have the time and/or resources to build it myself.</li>
<li>(&ndash;/0) Maybe someone else makes a profitable product faster than me. Thus he will act as a possible competition for me. Well, this might inevitably happen even if I publish my product earlier. Then he&rsquo;s called a fast follower. On the other hand every implementation is different (optimized for different goals), I might do better and also the market is usually big enough to offer room for both.</li>
<li>(+) Even if someone else make business upon my idea, new working places might be created and possibly I might be credited as the source of inspiration.</li>
<li>(+) Whatever happens, a good idea might attract likely minded people, start a discussion, or even live its own life beyond my control and eventually help people.</li>
<li>(+) This way I might build audience, a group of people that are interested in this kind of ideas, that might help further sharpen the ideas, encourage me to build a product and eventually help me spreading the word.</li>
<li>(+) Discussing the ideas with other people might help me recognize which ideas are really worth giving the energy into realizing them.</li>
<li>(+) In the long term it might help me building a better credit in the community, make new friends, and possibly be noticed for some interesting job or contract, or make better products alone or in cooperation with someone else.</li>
<li>(+) Something useful will remain after me.</li>
</ul>


<p>Probably you&rsquo;ll agree there are mostly possitives and the nagatives are in fact inevitable and actually not that bad. It feels a little bit like a step outside a comfort zone, but such actions are usually the most useful ones. I don&rsquo;t believe an idea can be &ldquo;owned&rdquo; (or more precisely &ldquo;squatted&rdquo;) by anyone, let alone the first one ever.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s like a seed. Sometimes it gets into your way and it&rsquo;s up to you how you utilize it. You can burn it for heating or grow a big plant from it.</p>

<p>For myself this means that sharing my vast shelf of ideas with the world seems to the best I can do now.</p>

<p>What do you think? Do you have a similar experience?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
